Abdul Basit

in https://www.linkedin.com/in/abdul-basit-319240151/

1 +92-305-8936334 ⊠ Islamabad, Pakistan

Hacker Rank



Professional Summary

A Backend Software Engineer with 5+ years of professional experience and a diverse set of competencies (mostly in Java and related technologies). I have worked in Fintech & Banking, Healthcare, ERP, and Petroleum sectors. I have experience of Java development in both monolithic & microservices architectures using Core Java, Java Swing, Java Fx, EJB, Spring Boot, Databases, CI/CD, Python & Amazon Web Services.

Work Experience

IBM (Pakistan) Dec 2021 - Present

Application Developer: Java and Web Technologies

Major Contributions: Working on the Internet and Mobile banking (IBMB) application of UAE's largest bank First Abu Dhabi Bank - FAB with following standouts:

- Integration of Abu Dhabi Pension Fund (ADPF) into the mobile banking of FAB. Now, a person can pay for his ADPF invoices, view history, generate payment statements, receive notifications, etc.

 The key features that were added as part of ADPF integration are Terms & Conditions for using ADPF, Consent Management for T&Cs, Add/Update/Delete ADPF Beneficiaries, Lookup Outstanding Invoice(s), Invoice Payments, Payment History, Download Transaction History in PDF, Email / SMS / Digital Notifications). At server-side, I was responsible for the design, development, and deployment of this payment feature.
- Integration of **NPSS** (Aani a real-time payments system introduced by the UAE government) into the mobile banking of FAB. Aani's feature allows UAE residents to make financial transactions through mobile number or email. Customers can now enroll/unenroll for Aani, perform SCA, make instant payments, pay through QR, request for payment, send money against a payment request, split bill, and view the dashboard & history.
- Development of a **Push Notification Engine** that pushes notifications in real-time and bulk. The engine can push notifications to millions of customers within minutes. The engine was developed using the AWS Push Notification feature.

The AWS services that were used to develop this engine are, SQS, SNS, S3 buckets, IAM (Roles & Policies), Lambdas & Layers (written in Python), DynamoDB, KMS, Secret Manager, Param Store, CloudWatch, API Gateway, VPC, CDK & CloudFormation.

- Functional enhancements in T24 by integrating T24 AA module changes.
- Exposure of Fund Transfer Limits to CRM, Beneficiary Name Validation by Iban through Central Bank
- Migration of Easy Buy, Balance Transfer / Quick Cash APIs from data power to CRM
- Enhancements in TFS (transaction fraud system). We moved code from legacy project into a new micro-service and used JMS (Java Message Queue) for message communication between both applications.
- Performance improvements in log masking by using Re2j library for pattern matching.
- Encryption/decryption mechanism using AES algorithm at app-side & backend.
- Removing high-risk security vulnerabilities from backend projects by updating and excluding all vulnerable transitive dependencies from pom files
- Documentation of multiple processes e.g. AWS CDK Setup & Stack Creation, Spring Boot v2 to v3 migration, Lambda / Layers change & deployment process.

Carecloud (MTBC)

Jan 2021 - Dec 2021

Software Engineer

Major Contributions: Worked on 2 different **EHR** products and following are some of my contributions: **Product – GO:**

- As part of the DMS team in GO, I worked on the implementation of uploading and downloading a document, rotate pages, split pages, annotate pages, previewing a document from multiple entry points. I have also worked on translation of Node JS APIs into Java Spring Boot microservices.
- As part of the Communications team in GO, I have worked on APIs for sending messages and notifications to
 patients when the status of a document is changed. We used Kafka as a messaging queue and wrote apis to
 produce and listen messages from our Kafka queue. In communications team, I worked on translating APIs to
 send messages, receive messages, add attachment to a message, reply to messages, open message screen

from different entry points.

• I worked with cross-regional team having colleagues from US, UK, India, Pakistan, Spain, Venezuela

Product - TalkEHR:

- I worked as a full stack developer (using Angular + .NET core) and worked on different features.
- I mainly worked on day-to day enhancements and features in Prescription, Medication and Diagnosis sections of the product and mainly worked on fixing bugs, adding enhancements and creating new APIs.
- Conducted a series of Unit Testing sessions across the organization in .NET core and xUnit.

Dbiz Solutions (Sidat Hyder Morshed Associates)

Mar 2019 - Jan 2021

2014 - 2018

Junior Programmer

Major Contributions: Worked on 2 different projects with following noticeable achievements:

Credit Management System (for Attock Petroleum):

Worked for the second largest petroleum company in Pakistan on its credit management project.

- Analyzed AS-IS and TO-BE documents and conducted sessions with client to develop different artifacts of SRS document.
- I supervised a team of 5 developers. I was responsible for assigning tasks, reviewing them and merging them into the main branch.
- Designed UI screens and APIs for the features to be developed. Some major features are Customer Account Creation, Customer Document Verification (Bank Guarantees, Letter of Credits, MOAs etc), Dispatch (of Product), Tank Lorry Tracking, Invoice Creation, Payment Receipts, General Ledger, and Reconciliation of the invoices.
- We also designed screens and APIs to integrate our payment in the app of HBL (Habib Bank Limited) Pakistan.

Real Estate Software (for DHA):

- Implemented GIS using MapBox geocoding API. When adding plots, if the location coordinates are provided, then the plot was created on Map automatically. I worked on Core Java Legacy App to implement this feature.
- Added barcode to Sales Invoice to achieve auto-reading of invoice for creation of payment receipts and reconciliations.
- Designed Screens in Mxml and Action Script for CRUD operations such as addition of land coordinates, schemes, plots, city, country. And the server-side coding was done in Core Java.

Education

International Islamic University Islamabad

Bachelor of Science in Software Engineering CGPA: 3.50/4.00

Dachelor of Science in Software Engine

Technical Skills

- Languages & Frameworks: Java (Core, EJB, Spring Boot, Swing), Microservices, Unit Tests (JUnits, Karate Framework), SQL, AWS (CDK, DynamoDb, Secret Manager, System Manager, IAM, Cloud Watch, Lambda, EC2, ELK Kibana, Fargate, KMS, Cloud Formation, S3, API Gateway), Kubernetes, Docker, MQs (JMS, Kafka), Caching (Redis), Maven, Gradle, Agile, C#, FHIR, Angular JS
- Tools: IntelliJ/Eclipse/STS, VS Code, Postman, WinSCP, Putty, Jira, Confluence, BPMN, AWS Console
- Databases: Oracle, MySQL (MySQL Workbench), MS SQL Server, PostgreSQL (pgAdmin), AWS-DynamoDb
- Version Control: Git (GitHub, Gitlab, Team Foundation Azure DevOps Server), CI/CD Pipeline

Courses/Certifications

- AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner Amazon Web Services
- Master Microservices With Spring Boot and Spring Cloud Udemy
- Java Programming Fundamentals Udemy
- Problem Solving (Intermediate) Certificate <u>Hacker Rank</u>
- Security and Privacy by Design Practitioner IBM
- Cognitive Practitioner IBM
- Business Communication and Ethics in Organizations Udemy
- Complete Algorithms Complexity and Big O Notation Course <u>Udemy</u>
- App Modernization Basics IBM
- Security and Privacy by Design Foundations IBM
- Problem Solving (Basic) Certificate <u>Hacker Rank</u>
- Enterprise Design Thinking Practitioner <u>IBM</u>

Languages: English (Proficient), Urdu/Hindi (Native) Interests: Movies, TV Series, Writing, Swimming